Sooyong Lee

PHD

Educational Psychology, The University of Texas at Austin

□ +1 737 865 0618 | Sooyongl09@utexas.com | □ 0000-0002-7964-4508 | □ sooyongl/

Professional Summary _____

As a psychometrician, I specialize in applying contemporary statistical theories and techniques to my work. My research interests center around developing and utilizing statistical models, including structural equation modeling (SEM), multilevel modeling (MLM), item response theory (IRT), and mixture modeling. In my recent work, I have placed particular emphasis on Bayesian estimation as a means of modeling the relationships between variables.

Education

The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, Texas

Ph.D., Major in Quantitative Methods in Educational Psychology

2017-2023

Korea University
Seoul, Republic of Korea

M.A., MAJOR IN EDUCATIONAL STATISTICS AND MEASUREMENT

2014-2017

Research experience _____

FLPS project Post-doc

IES GRANT 2023/9-present

Development of FLPS package for Fully-latent Principal Stratification

FLPS project

Graduate Research Assistant

2021/9-2023/8

• Development of FLPS package for Fully-latent Principal Stratification

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2021/6-2021/8

Internship for developing ESS package for Embedde Standard Setting

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2020/6-2020/8

Internship for developing Shiny app for Embedded Standard Setting

maat package development project

Graduate Research Assistant

NORTHWEST EVALUATION ASSOCIATION (NWEA)

2019/9-2020/5

Development of MAAT package for Computerized Adaptive Testing for Northwest Evaluation Association (NWEA)

COE Full-Time Tenured and Tenure-Track Faculty

Graduate Research Assistant

2019/9-2019/12

• Data analysis for surveys of graduate programs of education at the University of Texas at Austin

President's Award for Global Learning (PAGL)

Graduate Research Assistant

PRESIDENT'S AWARD FOR GLOBAL LEARNING (PAGL)

2019/1-2019/8

• Designing a culturally appropriate mobile application to increase mental health literacy and self-care habits among South Korean young adults

• Data analysis for surveys to collect data on the career pathways of past and present STEM and humanities PhD students.

Selective Publications

- Seung Choi, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Christina M. Schneider, Jay Lee, & Garron J. (2022). maat: An R Package for Multiple Administrations Adaptive Testing. *Applied Psychological Measurement*. 46-1, 73-74.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2022). DIF Detection With Zero-Inflation Under the Factor Mixture Modeling Framework. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. 82-4, 678-704.
- Jonghwan Lee, Christina Schneider, Garron Gianopulos, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Sangdon Lim, & Seung W Choi (2023). The Impact of Item Bank Transition Rules on Student Ability Estimates and Achievement Level Classifications. *Journal of Computerized Adaptive Testing*. In print.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2023). Bayesian Moderated Non-linear Factor Analysis for DIF Detection under Violation of Equal Variance Assumption. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. Under review.

Selective Presentation and Poster_____

- **Sooyong Lee** & Suhwa Han (2020-07). *Item selection and trait estimation methods in CAT with item leakage*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), Maryland, USA.
- Daniel Lewis & **Sooyong Lee** (2021-04). *A Comparison of Two ESS Cut Score Estimation Algorithms*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), Baltimore, MD, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2021-04). *DIF Detection with Zero-Inflation under the Mixture Modeling Framework*. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.
- Garron Gianopulos, Jay Lee, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, & Seung W. Choi (2022-04). *The Impact of Item Pool Size and Item Pool Distribution on Student Ability Estimates for a Hybrid Interim-Summative CAT*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.
- Jay Lee, M. Christina Schneider, Garron Gia, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Sangdon Lim, & Seung W. Choi (2022-04). *The Impact of item bank transition rules on student ability estimates and achievement level classifications*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.

Program_

Embeded Standard Setting

• https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/ESS shiny/

GRshiny: Graded response model

• https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/GRShiny/

Embeded Standard Setting

https://sooyongl.github.io/EmStanS/

maat package

• https://choi-phd.github.io/maat/

flps package

• https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/flps/index.html

GRshiny package
• https://sooyongl.github.io/GRShiny/

Shiny application

2021

Shiny application

2022

R package 2022

R package

2022

R package

2022

R package

2023